All right.
So, for this, the penultimate lecture for financial markets,
I wanted to talk about nonprofit and
government finance.
So, let me first recall some of the basic
themes of this course.
Finance is really about incentivizing people to do
good work and managing risks.
These issues are not confined
to the private sector, to the
business sector.
They're very deep and central problems to all people.
The big problem, to put it
in the most broad term, just
about everything that we do that's
good is done as part of
a team.
It's hard to think of something
that you alone can do.
And so, the problem with teams
is that people have their own
individual concerns and incentives, and it doesn't
always yield teamwork.
So, that's what I think finance is really about.
You might think I'm wrong, that some of the greatest
achievements in history were done by single individuals.
So, I don't know what you might think of.
What comes to my mind is, how about Albert Einstein?
He was a great scientist.
He had good design, right?
His theories.
He was sitting in a patent office in Switzerland, just
doodling on a piece of paper
and came up with a whole
theory of relativity.
You see, that would be
a mistake to think that, because
in fact, he had gotten a
PhD in physics from the Zurich
Polytechnic, which is a nonprofit organization.
And he relied on journals of physics.
He could not have done it without
the help of the field research group.
have done it, if he didn't read what other physicists
were doing.
And journals were organizations that had
financing, I assume non-profit.
I thought of another example.
Charles Darwin, the great physicist, not physicist, the
great naturalist.
People point out that he wasn't affiliated.
He was on his own.
He wasn't part of a university.
I guess he got financing,
but kind of on his own.
But he couldn't have written The Origin of
Species by himself.
In fact, he got financing
from private donors for the Beagle,
this two-year voyage he made around the world, where he
collected specimens and information.
It actually goes back to his professor.
He had a professor.
He was a professor at the University of New York,
Henry Henslow at Cambridge University, who was a botanist.
And Henslow arranged for Darwin's voyage and sent him
off.
So, you know, these are organizations that I don't
think you can do much good.
Some people would say, well, how about a poet?
A poet, sometimes they're even blind.
Homer was a blind poet, right?
He just.
He didn't have anything.
He didn't know how to write a poem.
He didn't know how to write it down.
He just memorized everything.
He just sat there and thought.
But even he must have had financing, because he traveled
around the world of his
day and made his poems known.
Otherwise, they wouldn't survive.
Other people learned them.
And he must have had financing for this.
It must have been a business.
So that's the general theme.
I'm going to talk today,
there's so much to talk about,
but I'm going to try to see
how much of this I can cover with.
I've got a couple more minutes.
But let me just finish first.
All right.
I've got one more.
I want to start by talking about nonprofit organizations.
These are organizations who have a purpose stated in their
charter, other than making money.
Okay?
And then I want to talk about government involvement in
for-profits, that for-profit companies are not completely
clear of a social interest as well.
Then I'm going to talk about government finance of projects.
And then finally, government social insurance.
I'm hoping that this lecture
will remind you of things that
you can do, because in all these sectors, there are
things that you can do.
So, one of the themes of
this course was, you should have a
purpose in life, and it should
not be making money, per se.
And think of finance as a purpose.
And you should have a purpose in life.
And think of finance as a tool
that you can use to help you
achieve this purpose.
So, that's what I want to talk about.
So, let me start then with nonprofits.
A nonprofit organization, it can
be a corporation that is an
organization set up for a charitable cause, or a good
cause.
And it has no
owners, in the sense that a regular corporate, there's no
shareholders.
The profits go back to the organization for its purposes.
So, right now, you're sitting,
as I mentioned before, Yale is
a nonprofit.
It has no owners.
It's a legal person in itself.
But it has a board of directors.
In the United States, in
2010, there were 1.6 million nonprofits.
It's huge.
Well, the U.S. is probably
the country that has the strongest
nonprofit sector.
My number for the United
Kingdom, maybe out of date, was
It's part of the U.S. culture that nonprofits are big.
It goes back to the founding
ideas of this country, that we
don't have the government running everything.
We do things on our own, on our own initiative.
Of course, it's not just the government.
It's not just the U.S.
There are nonprofits in every country.
But that's a lot of nonprofits.
And they recently accounted for about 4% of gross domestic
product.
So, it's okay.
It's not huge, but it's
a very important component of gross
domestic profit.
Okay.
I just wanted to start by thinking about nonprofits and
maybe put the idea in your head
of creating one at some point in
your life, sooner or later.
I thought I'd start with
some examples that are familiar to
me of nonprofits.
When you're thinking of some
activity or some idea you have,
you can set it up as for-profit or nonprofit.
And let's just think about why you would do that.
So, I'll give you an example.
Peter Tufano, he's a professor
at the Harvard Business School,
set up a nonprofit on
his own, just as a professor.
I know him.
And he gave it an inspirational name, Doorways to Dreams.
And it's about personal finance and about helping people do
things better in their personal financing.
So, one of his ideas, and
he's promoting it with, he raises
money for his foundation to promote it.
One of them is to have
an automatic check off on the tax
form, so that when you get
a tax refund, instead of getting
it in cash, it could go right into U.S.
savings bonds to encourage people to save.
This is based on behavioral finance
and the fact that a lot
of people, especially lower income people, don't save.
A little nudge like that would help the nonprofit.
A little nudge like that would help them save.
Another thing, this sounds like a
strange idea, but this is the
kind of thing he can pursue on
his own genius, as long as he
can raise money to get him to do it.
He has the idea that a lot
of people like to play the lottery.
Obviously, they do.
And they just are steady losers on this.
On average, they'll always lose.
But given that people want that, why don't we create
savings plans that pay out randomly, like winning the
lottery, so that the government doesn't have any
take in it?
It just encourages saving.
That's a strange, original idea, which you might find
hard to convince the government to do it.
But he can just do it.
He doesn't have to talk to the government.
He talks to individual banks.
And he's gotten some now to offer this plan.
But what was striking to me is,
he said, when I go into some
company trying to raise money,
I'm not going to do it.
I'm going to invest my money for my projects.
When I tell them I'm nonprofit, it changes the
whole atmosphere.
Because they know that I'm not profiting from this.
And so, it opens up opportunities.
I'll give you a second example.
Dean Carlin here at Yale,
he came here as an assistant
professor, in 2002, he created a charity called Innovations
for Poverty Action.
So, this is just a little bit.
Dean Carlin.
Some of you may have taken his course.
Anyone took his course?
Some of you, yeah.
Actually, the doorbell rang at
my house here in New Haven,
and a young woman was collecting money for charity.
And it was his charity.
I was shocked.
He's actually sending people door
to door, at least as part
of his course.
But since then, he's been doing it.
And since then, he's developed, again, with its
nonprofit, and it's aimed at alleviating poverty, he can
bring in lots of money.
So, right now, last year
in 2010, the income of his
Innovations for Poverty Action was $25 million.
And he has a staff of
500 people all over the world,
operating in a lot of poorer countries.
So, he's doing it.
And he's doing it for the people of New Haven.
So, that's a couple of examples that are familiar to
me, because they were set up by friends of mine.
Another example.
This is Bill Drayton.
He set up something called the Ashoka Foundation.
And he's a, what is it,
it's a ruler of India, who advocated
nonviolence and philanthropy.
And he went to Yale
Law School, as well as Harvard
College, sort of local here.
But it's been a huge
success, and it encourages sort of
entrepreneurship for social entrepreneurs.
But he didn't stay on as a professor.
He taught at Stanford Law
School, but dropped out of the
law school.
But dropped out, because he wanted to pursue his nonprofit.
So, I'm amazed that these two
guys can be both professors and
running big nonprofit shops, as well.
But some people can do that.
My last example is Wendy Kopp.
I like this example for
your age, because her story starts
with her senior essay.
Do you know this story?
She was an undergrad student.
She was a graduate at Princeton.
Graduated in 1989.
And she had to write, maybe
they call it a senior thesis.
And so, she wrote something about education.
She had an idea that often it's hard for elementary
education to find people who are passionately committed to
science or mathematics or other fields.
And she wrote, people typically don't want to devote their
lives to teaching, but they
might devote a couple years to
teaching.
And so, she thought that it
would be a good idea to get
people, when they graduate from college,
to spend a year or two
in elementary education.
And that it would be
refreshing and good for the educational
system, to get enthusiastic young people who are really
interested in the disciplines.
So, that was her senior thesis.
Now, of course, you can't get
the government to pay for this.
Maybe you could.
It might be hard.
Because, well, the teachers' union might not like this, or
they might, you know, it's sort of a controversial idea.
Some people would say, someone who's taken a course in
mathematics at Yale University is
really not qualified to teach
young children, because he or
she didn't take the educational
curriculum.
And that's always going to be controversial.
But here, when we live in a society that emphasizes
nonprofits, you don't have to convince the government, all
right?
You convince anybody to finance
this, and you can do it.
So, right out, she was 21 years old.
She graduated from Princeton.
She raised $2.5 million in her
first year to set up an
organization called Teach for America.
And they, the organization is called Teach for America.
And she directly visited the school.
She merely recruited young people who had just graduated
college to go into teaching.
So, anyway, that's become her life's work in the 20-plus
years since.
She's heading what she created.
I like this story, because
some of you are writing senior
essays, right?
And you should consider it as
a model for some, you might
consider it as a model for
some great idea that you might have
that you could carry to the world.
to make it happen is, if
it's that kind of idea, you just
set up a nonprofit right there.
Actually, I wanted to give you some other examples.
In New Haven, we have two major hospitals.
Where did they come from,
and why do we have them?
Well, one of them is called Yale New Haven.
So, how did that get started?
Well, it was started by
a nonprofit in 1826 called the
General Hospital Society of Connecticut.
Back then, there weren't many hospitals, and so someone set
up a nonprofit to set up
a hospital, and it was then the
only hospital in the United States.
And it was the only hospital in the United States.
It was the only hospital
in the state of Connecticut, and
so they called it State Hospital.
Later, as more hospitals appeared, it didn't seem good
to call it State Hospital anymore, so they changed the
name to New Haven Hospital.
That was in 1884.
And then, in 1913, they joined with another nonprofit called
Yale University.
And then later, they changed
their name to Yale New Haven
Hospital.
But it's been a nonprofit all the time.
Now, there are for-profit hospitals, but this one was
always a nonprofit.
The other hospital that we
have in New Haven is St.
Raphael's, and that's newer.
It was created in 1907, and
the story is that a group of
physicians from the New Haven
area thought we needed a second
hospital.
And they went to Sisters of
Charity, which is a nunnery, I
suppose, and worked with them to create a second hospital.
And they chose the name
Raphael after an archangel recognized
by many faiths, which means God has healed.
Now, why, it's interesting to think about this hospital.
So, whose idea was it, and how did it happen?
Well, apparently, the idea wasn't from the Sisters of
Charity, it was from physicians who were in New Haven.
So, why did they go to the Sisters of Charity?
Why didn't they just set up a for-profit hospital?
They could have bypassed them completely.
What's the link?
Well, I think that, I don't
know all of their reasons, but I'm
suspecting the reasons are, is
that when you affiliate with a
religious organization, it gives a sense of moral mission
and social purpose to the organization that it wouldn't
have otherwise.
And it makes it very clear that it's non-profit, and
encourages people to donate.
So, I think that this same
idea has dawned on many people.
The people who see a
need for a new hospital are
probably not leaders of churches, but they see a common
interest in pursuing hospitals.
So, there have been many studies about for-profit versus
non-profit hospitals, and who gives the better care.
I think that the studies are
generally inconclusive, because even people who are
donating for-profit hospitals have a social mission as well.
They have morals.
It's not just churches.
People outside of churches have morals as well.
And so, the actual distinction between
for-profit and non-profit is often somewhat ambiguous.
So let me now move on to the
over-the-counter.
I'm sorry.
Well, let me move on to the second point
that I said I was going to talk about, which
is government involvement in for-profits.
So, governments exert control
over both non-profits and for-profits.
And it's often hard to understand that.
difficult distinction between a government activity and a
private activity, because of the regulation that
governments impose over companies and the
taxes they collect.
So, let me first make
it clear that virtually every country
of the world has a substantial corporate profits tax.
And in that sense, governments are co-owners of
corporations, private.
So, the corporate profits tax
is, in effect, a sort of
partial nationalization of all the private
companies in the country.
So, in the U.S., it currently
stands at 35% federal and up
to 12% private.
So, that's the U.S.
state and local, depending on the state.
So, it's as high as 47%.
It's basically half.
So, you could say that the U.S.
government has nationalized close to half of the private
sector.
The government is collecting from their profits, as if they
were a shareholder.
This is state and local.
But it's the same in other countries, or similar.
Canada.
The Ottawa collects 16.5%, and the provinces up to 16%.
A little bit lower than the U.S.
Japan, the national government has a 40.6% profit tax.
Brazil, 34%.
So, that's the U.S. state.
You might think that under the Lula government, well, the
recent Lula government, they would be more left wing and
would have a higher profits tax, but they don't.
It's about the same.
China is 25%.
India is 33%.
And I could go on and on.
There's a lot of different countries.
So, that's the U.S. state.
There's almost no country that doesn't have it.
So, in that sense, everything is part of the government.
It's about the same all over
the world, and that's because I
think there's a reason for that.
Because if you charge too
high a profits tax, then business
will leave your country.
Why do we charge a profits tax?
Well, I think the corporate
value is that it's a very
important thing.
And the profits tax is justified by recognizing that
this thing about for-profit or private always has its
limitations.
And anything that's private is not completely isolated from
other interests or activities.
So, I thought it would be
useful to think of one example.
There's a company called TEPCO.
You've heard of this company?
I don't expect that you would.
It's the fourth largest electric power company in the
world, and it's traded in the U.S.
And you may own shares in
it and not know it, because it's
such a big and important company.
Or at least your parents, good
chance that they own shares in
it, because they probably own some diversified portfolio in
their pension plan, or maybe they
even have it set up in a
trust for you already.
So, don't worry about it.
It's a very important company.
I don't want to judge TEPCO too harshly.
All right.
But let me just tell
you about your investment in TEPCO.
Guess what country it's in?
You got it.
So, somebody know.
Why would that matter right now?
Big electric power company in Japan?
That's not a great investment.
Yeah?
They own the power plant.
That's right.
They own, particularly, the Fukushima power plant.
And they own the power plant.
So, I checked out this morning
what the share price is going
for in TEPCO.
So, it was, as of a
month or so ago, $25 a share.
And it's down to $5 a share.
It just went, phoom!
And you know exactly why.
So, I looked this further.
J.P. Morgan estimates now that claims against TEPCO will be
$25 billion, or a couple trillion yen.
But that's not all.
They're also damaged, right?
Everything's in ruins.
So, some people are predicting that TEPCO will go bankrupt.
All right?
So, they've done all this, they've created this whole mess
in Japan, and they're just going to go bankrupt.
And we have limited liability, right?
They're not going to come after you, right?
The Japanese government could do diligence and find out that
you own shares in TEPCO.
And TEPCO was negligent, right?
Right?
They messed up.
They didn't do their safety procedures well enough.
But they'll never go after you.
I mean, this is the whole idea of limited liability.
So many people all over the
world are owning shares, and we
can't expect them to be responsible for it.
You can't inspect the Fukushima
plant, even though you may be
a beneficiary of its profits.
So, that's why they collect the money.
They collect the money.
And they collect the corporate profits.
So, Japan is collecting 40% corporate profits tax, and that
can be used to offset the damages that the Japanese
government now has to pay for.
So, it all seems right.
There's a plan here.
So, you wonder, is TEPCO private or not?
Well, it is private, in the sense that there are
shareholders and there are profiters, but it's regulated
by Japan, it's taxed by
Japan, and Japan pays for their
mistakes.
So, that's TEPCO.
Thank you.
That's typical.
So, I'll give you another example from this country.
General Motors, okay?
General Motors was the biggest car company in the United
States, and then it had a little problem during the
financial crisis.
And it had a problem.
And it had to file for Chapter 11 bankruptcy.
Now, you know, what am I
referring to when I say Chapter
The Bankruptcy Act has chapters, okay?
And each chapter says something different.
The two most important chapters
for companies is Chapter 7 and
Chapter 11.
Okay?
And what the bankruptcy law says
is, it says, it's not a good
idea.
It's not a good idea.
It's a bad idea.
And what the bankruptcy law
does is, it creates a framework
for dealing with insolvency.
And the framework says that a
company that is in trouble can
choose to apply for bankruptcy.
And there's basically two important ways to do that.
Chapter 7 details one way
you can apply for bankruptcy, and
Chapter 11 details another way.
Okay?
Chapter 7 is liquidation.
That means that the company
is in such trouble that we're
going to shut it down
and sell off all the assets.
Chapter 11 is for a
company that is in trouble, but
there's something worth salvaging in terms of operating,
continuing the business.
So, that's what GM chose to do.
That's what they did.
Okay?
Thank you.
Okay.
All right.
So, we're going to close Chapter 11 bankruptcy.
They thought, obviously, we're making cars for now close to
100 years.
Well, at least the companies
that went together to form GM.
And we have a big future.
So, we can't pay our
bills now, but we should continue.
So, they filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy.
government and the Canadian government invested in GM.
What happened was, General Motors, they changed the name
in the most subtle way.
The official name of the company was General Motors
Corporation.
Okay?
When they filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy, the shareholders
were wiped out.
Nobody got executed.
You lost all your money.
And so, if you find
in your attic some nice, beautiful
share certificates for General Motors Corporation, you can
just use them as wallpaper or whatever.
They're worthless.
But if it's different, if it says General Motors Company,
because that refers to the new
GM, they wanted to change the
name, but they didn't really want to change the name.
They had to change the name, so that people wouldn't
confuse the two.
So what happened?
How did we get a new GM?
Well, it's a good question.
Well, the new GM was owned by the U.S. government.
It was equal to 60.8% U.S. Canada owned 12%.
The UAW, United Auto Workers.
Got 17.5%.
Why did the union, by
the way, get 17% of GM?
Well, I don't know the whole
story, but I'm sure it has
something to do with GM's obligations.
Maybe they failed on something.
I don't know the details.
But it seemed in the
bankruptcy proceedings that the implicit
debts that the company owed to their workers would be
represented.
And the company was represented
by a share in the company.
And then the rest went
to the bondholders, people who own
debt, not equity, who own debt
in GM, got the remaining share.
And they also got warrants,
which are options to buy more
shares, which will dilute down
the U.S. and Canada and UAW
shares.
So, that's the settlement.
The result of the settlement
was that it was a government-owned
organization.
Now, they've just done an IPO, so they're reversing this
ownership structure.
But the point is that companies
that look private may end up
government eventually, one time or another.
And so, companies have to kind
of think of themselves as a
government.
And that's the problem.
Because even in the arch-capitalist country, like
the United States, there's partly government
organizations.
By the way, there's
something else called personal bankruptcy.
And personal bankruptcy is another involvement of the
government in risk management.
So, you can choose to
declare bankruptcy, and you can choose
these chapters, or you can
do these other provisions as well.
But you can use Chapter 7
to wipe out all of your debts.
The new bankruptcy law that
Congress passed a few years ago
attempts to limit your ability
to do that, but within limits.
The same government is kind of a shareholder.
It's a shareholder, just as individuals are.
So, I mean, the shareholder and individual's lifetime
incomes.
I guess what I'm saying is
that the whole idea of public versus
private is a complicated one.
And what seems public at
one time will seem private at
another.
But the behavior of nonprofits is not strikingly different
than the behavior of profits.
So, I found a statistic
that 42% of nonprofits pay bonuses
to their executives.
That is, they're using the
same kind of incentive plans that
private corporations do.
Well, they do that because they have to hire people.
And people in the for-profit sector are getting bonuses.
So, how do you hire someone
and get someone good, unless you
pay the bonus as well?
The government faces a big
problem in that the public is
very sensitive to paying high salaries to government
employees, because they think it's unfair.
Why should some government bureaucrat be paid more than I
get?
Because they're not going to pay the money.
As a result, they have trouble hiring good people.
But in the nonprofit sector, the nonprofit sector is not
constrained, well, they have some constraints over, they're
regulated to prevent them from stealing the money.
But I think part of the
idea of having nonprofits, this is a
general point, is that the government is kind of confined
to the
government.
And they can do things
that are just generally acknowledged by
the average person as a good thing.
And that's why some of our biggest progress is made.
So, I gave the example of Charles Darwin and his
professor, who advocated his voyage around the world.
The professor, I'm trying to
see what his name, Henslow, I
think it was, was actually a John Stevens Henslow, a
botanist, but also an advocate of natural theology.
And he sent Darwin out on
this voyage, because he thought that
studying nature enabled you to discover God.
Little did he know, Darwin
would end up an atheist after
his voyage.
But it's this kind of weird stuff that gets financed.
Or Wendy Kopp, I gave
another example, whose ideas were too
controversial.
I mean, the idea of sending
someone out who didn't have an
education diploma to teach.
Too controversial.
So, I think that there
is maybe a growing recognition of
the importance of having people
who are, well, there's a term,
social entrepreneurs.
These are, I don't know
whether they're for-profit or nonprofit,
but they're people who do
things out of a sense of
mission for beyond making money, but helping the world.
And you see this reported in newspapers and magazines, that
the 21st century seems to be
a century where there's more and
more of this kind of thing.
And it's substantial.
Substantial measure, I think, nonprofit.
Okay, then now I wanted to
move to the third thing, which I
said is municipal or state and local finance.
It's a big topic, but an awful
lot of what gets done in this
country is done by state and local governments.
It's something on the order,
it's something on the order of
the federal government.
It's bigger than the federal government.
The state and local governments
spend about twice as much money
as the U.S. federal government.
They run all the public schools, fire departments, police
departments, most of the parks.
What else?
I mean, a lot of things
are being run by state and local
governments.
And so, I think another thing that
one could do is to have a
government that's more than just
a state and local government.
And I think that's what one
could do to make things happen
in the world.
I mentioned the possibility of setting up a nonprofit.
You can make things happen by doing that.
But you can also make
things happen by approaching a local
government and saying to them, I
think that you would do well
to build a hospital or build
a bridge or build a new school,
or even kind of business-oriented things that
would be projects that the government can undertake.
And then they can finance it
as a state and local government.
Now, one thing in the
United States, every state in the
United States has a balanced budget rule.
That is, they have to
tax people for all of the
expenditures they make.
They are not allowed to go into debt.
But we have to be careful
about what the balanced budget rules
in their constitution say.
Because obviously, there is municipal debt.
Governments do borrow money.
State and local governments in the United States, they have
a balanced budget.
And the governments in the United States have typically
– it differs across states
– but they typically have two
budgets.
They have an operating budget and a capital budget.
The operating budget is what
has to be balanced according to
their constitutions.
So, the operating government budget involves a list of all
the expenditures they made for operations and the taxes.
And they cannot – it differs
by state and how it's worded,
but they cannot plan to
run a deficit in some state.
Or if they do run a
deficit on the operating budget, they have
to correct it soon and have
a plan for correcting it soon.
But the capital budget is different.
It also – if a city
builds a new school, for example, that's
not an operating expense, right?
It's a capital expense.
So, it's building something that will last through the
ages.
And so, it goes on the
capital budget and not on the operating
budget.
And all of the states allow this.
They can raise money by borrowing, and they routinely
do that.
So, that means they get into
debt, and then they have a
potential for going bankrupt as well.
So, this is the way –
imagine that you're setting up a small,
a new town, and it's small right now, okay?
Little town, but we know that
people are coming this way, and
it's going to be a
big town in 20, 30 years.
So, what do we do?
Well, you lay out the streets,
and you plan for a big town.
Right now, you better plan for it, right?
Or it'll get congested.
So, you better lay out wide enough streets.
That's easy to do.
You don't have to build a lot of streets.
But you kind of want to
build the streets before the people
come.
You have the layout, and you
have lots, and you have it all
planned.
And how about a sewage system?
The people aren't here yet, okay?
And so, you construct, you consult a sewage engineer, and
the engineer tells you, you
know, if you're going to build
a sewage system, you should do it all at once.
You don't have to do it
year after year, just adding a
little bit, a little bit.
You got to have a plan.
You have an idea where the city is going.
Let's build it for a city of 20,000 people.
We can do it now, but
it will cost you, you know, $100
million.
So, what do you do?
You might say, we can't pay for that.
There's only 30 people living in this town.
How do we come up with $100 million?
Obviously, you borrow, right?
You put it on the capital budget.
And that is fair and just, right?
And then, as people come to
the city, they will then pay
taxes and pay back the debt.
This is the way it works,
and it's the way it's always worked.
Now, you could say, well,
no, it shouldn't be this way.
Why don't we have all of
the individual people pay for their
own sewers and add to the
sewer system as they build their
houses?
It's not going to work, right?
That would be crazy.
You've got to build the whole system in advance.
And so, that's what we're going to do.
And that's what city governments do routinely.
And they go deeply into debt
as a result of having created
all of these capital investments and having the debt
against them.
So, your city that has
20 people is borrowed $100 million,
and it's going to be a
city of 20,000 people, it thinks.
And what if it doesn't work?
What if they don't come?
Your plan was wrong.
Then the city is at risk of going bankrupt, right?
So, there's another whole chapter for municipal
bankruptcy, Chapter 9 of the Bankruptcy Code.
And Chapter 9 is for city government.
There's a problem is that cities going bankrupt are
different, because they don't have any shareholders, right?
They do have an ability to tax people.
The question of how much
you should tax people in a
bankrupt city, if you tax
them too much, they'll just all
leave.
So, it's a subtle problem.
But fortunately, there haven't been, and I'm not sure we
really understand why, there have not been many municipal
bankruptcies at all.
And between 1975, okay, I'm sorry,
do I have data on it?
I thought I had data on numbers of bankruptcy.
You know, there are some famous municipal bankruptcies.
New York City went bankrupt,
or was about to declare bankruptcy
in the 1970s, but it was saved by bailouts.
Maybe that's the reason why we don't.
Basically, when New York City said that
it couldn't pay its debts, it was
going to pay its debts.
But New York City said
that it couldn't pay its debts.
The state of New York came by with a bailout.
And then also, although reluctantly and with a lag, the
U.S. federal government came in with a bailout.
So, big city, so New York never declared bankruptcy.
A lot of cities will have
what's called a rainy day fund.
And they will accumulate assets
to help them over troubled times.
So, you can collect somewhat
higher taxes, and then you have
an endowment.
The city has an endowment,
which can help tide them over
through difficult times.
But recently, most of the
rainy day funds have been exhausted.
So, they're not going to pay their debts.
They're going to be exhausted.
The state and local governments saved
for a rainy day, and this
was a rainy day, this financial crisis.
And so, most state and
local governments are in trouble right
now because of the recession causing their tax revenues to
decline, and there's increasing worry about municipal
bankruptcies.
So, I said that there
haven't been many historically, but the
people are edgy now, thinking
that there could be some now
because of the financial crisis.
And so, the yields on municipal bonds have gone up.
So, municipal bonds are tax-free in the United States.
So, if the city of New
Haven issues debt, and you buy the
debt, you are not going to pay the debt.
You are not subject to federal
income tax on the interest that
you earn.
That's because in the Constitution, it says that
there's a separation between federal and state.
The federal cannot tax the
state, so they don't tax your
municipal bond.
There's a subsidy toward municipal bonds implicit in the
tax law.
By the way, let me just mention.
The fact that municipal bonds
issued by local governments are
not subject to taxes extends as well to Yale University.
So, Yale University issues bonds that are in the same
category as municipal bonds, and they're not taxed.
So, there's an advantage, a tax advantage, and especially
higher-income investors like to invest in municipal bonds.
Because it matters more for higher-income investors, because
the tax rate hits them
more, and so there's an advantage.
So, Yale issues municipal bonds,
and Yale is an important debtor.
Now, you might wonder about that.
So, let's talk about Yale as a municipal bond issuer.
Yale has an endowment of $16 billion.
As of last year.
And it has a debt of $2.5 billion.
So, that leaves Yale with only
$13.5 billion in assets after debt.
So, you might say, why does Yale borrow money?
Right?
I mean, it's got $16 billion to invest in.
Why is it borrowing?
Well, there are many reasons, I suppose.
But the immediate and obvious
reason that comes to mind is
that Yale borrows money, because it
can borrow at a tax-subsidized rate.
Right?
If Yale's debt is not subject
to income tax, then that means it
can borrow at a lower rate.
And Yale would be inclined,
or any nonprofit that can issue
non-taxable debt.
And they would like to do that, in
order to invest in assets that are taxable.
Because Yale doesn't pay any taxes on either of them.
So, you see what I'm saying?
The municipal debt has a lower yield in the market.
Because everybody knows it's not subject to
income taxes, so it has a low yield.
So, Yale could issue that debt and use
the money to invest in high-yielding things that
are taxable.
And it's not going to pay taxes on them, either.
So, there's an arbitrage game that Yale
could play, or any nonprofit could play.
But it does not, because it's not
allowed to, unless it's investing, unless it's using
the proceeds of the debt for appropriate causes.
So, you have to understand, this is why
Yale University has a substantial debt, and why
Haven has a substantial debt.
It all makes sense in some basic finance framework.
But there's a lot of concern about
indebtedness right now, because with the financial crisis,
the U.S. and Europe and many other
countries are suffering debt crises right now.
So, it's renewing calls for a balanced budget amendment.
The U.S. government does not have a
balanced budget amendment like the state governments
do.
And in fact, the U.S. government has only one budget.
It does not have a capital budget.
So, in some sense, the state governments
are more sophisticated than the federal government
in the U.S., in that they have
the distinction between operating and capital budgets.
But I guess the reason why the U.S.
The U.S.
government has considered the U.S.
government as adopting a capital budget,
but it has never done so.
I think maybe it's because the U.S.
government has fewer investments, like schools
or parks or other water facilities, sewage
facilities.
It doesn't do that kind of thing.
So, it doesn't have as many clearly capital projects.
It has a much bigger debt
than the state and local governments.
Okay.
So, I guess then I'll move to my
last topic today, which is about government social insurance.
And this is along the same theme.
I'm talking today about the
roles of a financial institution.
The roles of finance is about
risk management, and it's about incentivization.
Some of the basic roles are classified under
the rubric of social insurance, which is offered
by the government.
And this is a huge topic.
And let me just say this.
Social insurance refers to insurance that is
not available by a private insurance company,
but that are offered generally by governments.
And let me just give some examples.
I put in first, progressive taxes.
Okay.
So, progressive taxes are income taxes that
tax higher income people at a lower rate.
And progressive taxes have increasingly,
in recent years, adopted something analogous
to the Earned Income Tax Credit, the EITC.
That's the U.S. name for it.
And it's now in many countries around
the world that provides negative taxes for the
lowest income people.
So, the effect of progressive taxes with Earned
Income Tax Credit is to insulate people somewhat
from shocks to their income.
They call it an Earned Income Tax Credit,
by the way, because you have to have earned
income to get the credit.
You can't be just unemployed.
But if you are working and earning very
little, especially if you have a family, then you
have a negative income tax rate, so that
the government augments your low income with a
negative tax.
I think this is very
important, and it actually is effective.
Otherwise, the world would be much
more unequal than it is now.
I would add, by the way, public services,
which are offered out of taxes to everyone
in a country, notably education.
School systems are generally free.
And that is, again, something that these are
all, I consider these a form of insurance,
because they benefit people.
They benefit people who are unsuccessful in earning money.
So, it's like an insurance program against
possible failure in achieving status in the
economic system.
So, we also have, I'll
go up here, three, Social Security.
I'm using U.S. terms.
These are terms that, these things
happen in virtually all advanced countries.
In the U.S., we call it OASD.
That stands for Old Age Survivors and Disability Insurance.
Old Age Insurance is pensions.
And that's the biggest part of the
Social Security system in the United States.
It's insuring you again.
Well, it's really something you know is going to happen.
You're going to get old someday.
But we call it insurance.
Survivors insurance is life insurance.
I mean, it benefits you.
You're getting too old for this now, but if your
parents die when you're young, they're going to get old.
So, it's a great insurance.
It's a great income.
The U.S. government will give you an income.
You're an orphan.
You have nothing.
Your parents died and left you nothing.
You get Survivors Insurance.
You didn't know you had this, right?
It's not publicized a lot, but it's part of
what protects people, and it's offered by the government.
And then thirdly, Disability Insurance.
Again, offered by the government.
It's not against you breaking your neck and becoming paralyzed, or
anything like that, that makes it impossible for you to work.
The U.S. government will give you an income for life.
So, if you are permanently paralyzed,
you get an income for life.
All three of these are purchasable in the private sector.
You can buy a pension.
You can buy Survivors Insurance.
They don't call that.
They call it life insurance.
It's just turning it around to a different name.
The sellers of life insurance don't want to remind you
that you already have a life insurance policy from the government.
Because you might say, well, I got enough already.
So, they give it a different name, and
they probably won't remind you that you have it.
And then you can buy Disability Insurance.
But part of the problem with private offering
of these insurances, Disability Insurance, if it's offered privately,
is that it's not going to be a disability.
It's going to be a selection bias problem.
That some people who realize that they are going
to have a disability will buy the insurance right away.
And then we have health insurance.
I don't want to use the U.S. as an example for
this, because we're kind of a laggard on most of these things.
But we had a new health
bill that passed under Obama last year.
And it's starting to gear up.
But the U.S. is not
the world leader in health insurance.
But it has currently about 40
million people with no health insurance.
And then there's workers' compensation.
These are the main aspects of social insurance today.
Workers' compensation is an older form of health insurance.
That preceded health insurance.
At least in the United States.
And it compensates workers for
accidents that occurred at work.
And in the U.S., this
came in in the Progressive Era.
But all these are risk management
devices that are offered by governments.
Now, these social insurance schemes are really important.
They're relatively recent innovations.
And in fact, I think that the first national, I know that, the
first national social insurance programs began in Germany in the late 19th century.
So, another theme of this course has been
that the ability to do things like this,
requires a developed society with a certain technology.
With an information technology,
with a bureaucratic technology.
And they haven't been around for that long.
If you go back in history, 200, 300
or more years, there wasn't social insurance anywhere.
Maybe there was in some isolated community.
But basically, it didn't exist.
And so, the history of social insurance is interesting.
And I think it mimics,
it reflects information technology growth.
So, the country that is most remarkable
for having invented social insurance is Germany.
Under Otto von Bismarck.
In the 1880s.
And I think that it happened
there first, because of the information technology.
But it's an interesting story.
There were various attempts to start social
insurance in different parts of the world,
that were half-hearted and failed.
In the United Kingdom, in the late
1700s, there was a town called Spanumland.
A tiny town in the UK.
That decided they would start social insurance.
And they decided that there was a living
wage that anyone ought to be able to earn.
And anyone who earned less than that,
would have the difference paid by the town.
So, the town, it's called the Spanumland Law.
And that town was called Spanumland.
And that town offered to pay the difference.
The problem was, it didn't work.
Too many people reported that they were getting
less income than the living income that they defined.
And the town discovered it was being ripped off.
And so, they couldn't, the problem is, they
couldn't identify what a person's income really was accurately.
They couldn't tell whether someone was goofing off or not.
And so, they dropped it.
It was, I think there are
other examples of failed experiments like this.
But, it took hold first in Germany in the 1880s.
And they got accident insurance.
Health insurance.
And old age insurance, or retirement.
For everyone in Germany in the 1880s.
And it was considered a fiasco
by other countries of the world.
When Germany announced these plans to create social
insurance, the London Times wrote an article saying,
this whole thing is a fiasco.
This whole thing will fall through and fail.
The government is going to run all of these insurance policies for something like, I
don't know how many, I think there were 11 million workers in Germany at the time.
And in London they said, you've got to be kidding.
No government in the world has
ever managed to run something like this.
Let's think particularly about retirement insurance.
The German government set up a plan whereby people would
contribute over their working lives to the Social Security system.
And the system would then, years later, 30, 40
years later, keep a tab about how much they'd contributed.
And then pay them a pension
for the rest of their lives.
So, the Times wondered aloud, are
they going to mess this up?
They've got to keep records for 40 years.
They were talking about the government keeping records.
And they thought nobody can really manage to
do this, and that it will collapse and ruin.
But it didn't.
The Germans managed to do this
in the 1880s for the first time.
And actually, it was an idea
that was copied all over the world.
So, why is it that Germany
was able to do something like this?
Why?
Because it was a very important thing.
It was a very important thing.
And it was a very important thing for the German government to be able
to do something like this in the 1880s, when it was not doable anywhere else.
It had never been done until that time.
I think this has to do ultimately with technology.
And technology, particularly information technology, was
advancing rapidly in the 19th century.
So, what happened in Europe that made
it possible to institute these radical new ideas?
So, I just give a list of one thing.
Paper.
This is information technology, but you don't think.
In the 18th century, paper,
ordinary paper, was very expensive.
Because it was made from cloth in those days.
They didn't know how to make paper from wood.
And it had to be handmade.
As a result, if you bought a newspaper
in, say, 1790, it would be just one page.
And it would be printed on the smallest print.
Because it was just so expensive.
It would cost you like $20
in today's prices to buy one newspaper.
Then they invented the paper machine.
That made it mechanically.
And they made it out of wood pulp.
And suddenly, the cost of paper went down.
By the way, I found an
old textbook from Yale University from 1837.
It's still sitting there on the shelf in the library.
I was looking.
We were using a Principles of
Economics textbook for all Yale students.
They all had to take the same course.
And it was a nice little book.
But it was so small.
I picked it up.
I mean, it was so small.
It was like that big.
You could put it in your pocket.
I think it's because books were just expensive.
You have these huge textbooks now, right?
They weigh so much.
They probably challenge your back.
Back then, you could carry your books.
There was a fundamental economic difference.
And so, paper was one of the things.
And you never got a receipt for anything.
When you bought something, you go to a store
and buy something, you think you'd get a receipt?
Absolutely not.
You would buy a copy of something.
Well, they wouldn't know why.
But that's the ultimate reason.
Too expensive.
So, they invented paper, too.
Carbon paper.
Do you people even know what this is?
Anyone here heard of carbon paper?
Maybe.
I don't know.
It used to be that when you wanted to make
a copy of something, you didn't have any copying machines,
you just had to write on it.
I don't know if I
have to explain this to you.
You know what carbon paper is?
You put it between two sheets of paper, and you write
on the upper one, and it comes through on the lower one.
This was never invented until the 19th century.
Nobody had carbon paper.
You couldn't make copies of any.
There was no way to make a copy.
They hadn't invented photography yet.
They had no way to make a copy.
You had to just hand copy everything.
And so,
the first copying machine, maybe I mentioned
that, didn't come until the 20th century.
And they were photographic.
And the typewriter.
That was invented in the 1870s.
Now, it may seem like a small thing, but it
was a very important thing, because you could make accurate documents.
And they were not subject
to misinterpretation because of sloppy handwriting.
I'm doing sloppy handwriting here for you.
But,
I'm using the old technology here.
the typewriter, and you could also make many copies.
You could make six copies at once with carbon paper.
And they're all exactly the same.
You can file them in a different,
each one in a different filing cabinet.
For standardized forms,
these are forms that had fill
in the blank with the typewriter.
They had filing cabinets.
And finally,
bureaucracy developed.
They had management school, particularly in Germany.
It was famous for its
management schools and its business schools.
So, you had,
oh, I should add also postal service.
If you wanted to mail a letter in 1790,
you'd have trouble.
And it would cost you a lot.
Most people in 1790 got maybe one letter a year,
or two letters a year.
That was it.
But,
in the 19th century, they started setting
up post offices all over the world.
And the Germans were particularly good
at this kind of bureaucratic thing.
So, there were post offices in every town.
And the Social Security system
operated through the post offices.
Because once you have post offices in every town,
you would go to make your payments on Social Security
at the post office.
And they would give you stamps,
and you'd paste them on a card.
And that's what they did.
And that's how you could show that you had paid.
So, I think that this kind of information technology
brought us the Social Security system.
And the kinds of advances in
information technology that we've seen more recently
will eventually lead to changes in the system.
Ultimately, technology drives finance.
And the system responds to changes in technology.
All right.
So, I just wanted to just wrap up.
I talked today about a broader
social purpose that's served by our finance.
And it takes place in terms of for-profit.
As well as non-profit.
But the distinction between for-profit
and non-profit is a subtle one.
I think what happens is, people think of a purpose,
of something they want to achieve.
And then they think, how
can I use our financial technology
to incentivize people to subscribe capital to this project,
or to give their personal attention to this project.
And then we have,
our system of finance has a lot of things,
a lot of devices that
can allow the provenance of capital.
And that allow, and that will incentivize people.
So, I think another theme of
this course has been behavioral finance.
That I think people are psychological.
They have emotions.
And they react in complicated ways.
One of the oldest themes of
economics is that people respond to incentives.
But they respond to, please to their morality as well,
or their ideals as well.
When we talk about non-profit sector,
it seems that the financial arrangements reflecting,
the combination of selfish money oriented incentives,
and more social purpose incentives.
And the same thing goes with government activities.
Anyway, I guess I have one more lecture,
and I'm going to talk next time
more broadly about what finance offers us,
and how it allows us to achieve social purposes.
And thanks so much for being here.